Hello, everybody.
This session
is lung session on
obstructive lung disease.
We have a separate one for
the restrictive
lung diseases.
This is doctor Plummer.
And really we're
going to talk about
just four main
diseases today and
they're listed in bold
in the session objectives.
For definition, a chronic
obstructive
lung disease by
the World Health
organization
is, as it shows there,
some kind of
disease that has
a persistent
respiratory symptom
and air flow limitation
because their there's
airway abnormalities,
and it's caused by
usually exposure
to noxious
particles or gases.
This is the fourth leading
cause of death
in the world.
It is very, very strongly
associated with
cigarette smoking.
These are some pulmonary
function test charts,
which a pulmonologist
would know more about.
But basically,
in all obstructive
lung diseases
that we're going to
talk about, the four,
there's an increased
resistance to air flow,
and it could be
because of partial or
complete obstruction
at any level.
The thing to
remember is that
the residual volume and
the total lung
capacity are both
going to be up because
the lungs are going to
be very, very full.
They're going to
be very compliant.
And the real thing
to remember is that
the FEV one FVC ratio
is usually under 0.7
CM in obstructive
lung disease.
Okay. This is from Robins,
and it just shows
the overlap
between the chronic
obstructive lung diseases.
Robins also includes
bronchiactsis,
which some people don't,
but we will talk about
bronchiactsis as well.
So let's start
with emphysema.
There are four
different types.
Basically, it's
enlargement of
the air spaces distal
to the terminal bronchial,
and it's usually it is
irreversible because the
walls are destroyed.
There's four types,
center asinar,
Panasonar, paraseptal,
and irregular.
The two that we're
really going to talk
about are the panast,
and the center
actin which are
shown in the picture
on the lower right.
So what is the
central acinar
is also known as
central lobular.
It is the most
common type,
most likely going to be
associated with
smoking cigarettes.
Here the central or
the proximal parts of
the asini are what are
affected and the distant
alveoli are spared.
But you can
have basically,
you can have
both bsminus and
normal air spaces in
the same acinus
and module.
This tends to happen in
the upper lobes and in
the apical segments.
Now, the panacinar,
also known
as pandular emphysema is
really mostly related to
Alpha one antitrypsin
deficiency,
which I'll talk about
a little bit more.
That is Alpha
one antitrypsin
is a protease inhibitor,
an enzyme inhibitor,
and if you don't
have an inhibitor,
the enzymes will
break down things,
and the walls
get broken down.
So here, the acini are
uniformly enlarged
all the way from the
respiratory bronchial
to terminal alveoli,
and usually the
lower lobes and
the anterior margins are
involved and more
severe at the bases.
And here's just a
visual of that,
that normal acinus
is shown in A,
and you can see
the center aciner,
and the panacinar
emphysema,
and that's the way we can
visualize what's going on.
Now, a little bit
about panacinar.
As I mentioned,
Alpha one antitysin,
just as an aside,
I want you to
know that this is
found in the blood,
zero, tissue
fluids, macrofages,
and it inhibits proteases,
specifically elastase.
Elastase is an enzyme
that's created by
the neutrophals when
there's inflammation.
So people of Alpha one
antitrypsin have
a deficiency.
And this is encoded
on the PI locus
chromosome 14,
which I don't
need you to know,
somebody may, but I
don't need you
to know that.
But I do need you to know
that the form the
homozygous form
Z Z is really
represents 0.012% of
the US population,
and those people
have very,
very low amounts of
Alpha one antitrpin,
and in fact, 80% of
them get panacinar
emphysema.
By the way, that is also
associated with
liver cirrosis,
and if they smoke,
it just makes
it even worse.
You have to realize
in any injury
that when you smoke,
that will increase
the neutrophils
in the area,
the activation,
the influx of
the neutrophils
into the lungs.
And these neutrils
will release
the proteases.
When you don't have
alpha one antitrpin,
you're going to get
excessive digestion
of elastic tissue.
Briefly about paraceptal
and irregular.
Paraseptal is also
known as distal aster.
You should keep
that in mind.
Sometimes they like
to reverse the words.
This is one that
is shown all the
way at the right,
which tends to
be something
that causes spontaneous
pneumothorax,
especially in young men.
The proximal part of
the acinus is normal,
but the distal part
is mostly involved,
and this is
especially true
when it's adjacent
to the plural.
And it occurs also
adjacent to areas of
fibrosis scar or altsis,
more severe in the upper
half of the lungs,
and sometimes the
spaces get so big that
they form what
are known as
buli or blisters or cysts,
really large
things that can
pop and cause a
pneumothorax,
and that is where
the problem is.
Finally, the
fourth type of
emphysema is
called irregular,
and it means it's
regularly involved,
and there's usually scar
tissue associated with it.
This one is clinically
asymptomatic,
and we're not going to
discuss much further.
As far as pathogenesis,
We're talking
about injury,
toxic injury and
inflammation,
especially from
cigarette smoke
in the center asiner,
and that damages the
epithelium of the lung,
and it causes
inflammation,
and you're going to get
destruction of the lung.
There are a lot
of inflammatory
mediators that
are involved,
and they're going to
be increase in
those areas,
and I've shown a few
in the parentheses.
Where do they come from?
The mediators come from
resident epithelial
cells and macrophages.
They attract inflammatory
cells from circulation,
amplify the
inflammation and
cause the
structural changes.
There is basically
a imbalance between
the protease and anti
protease in the lung,
and the proteases are
released from the
inflammatory cells,
and epithelial cells break
down the connected
tissue components.
There's also an oxidative
stress component,
where in the substance in
cigarette smoke and
ambo damage and
inflammatory cells,
all these things
are oxidants
that can cause
tissue damage.
They can also cause
endothelial dysfunction
and inflammation.
It's important to know
that infection though
doesn't cause emphysema,
it can make it worse.
This is a nice overview
of the things I was
just talking about.
This is more visual
for people who are
more visual and all
the suffect leading to
alveol wall struction.
Okay. This is
another picture.
It's a little bit
more detailed.
It shows the tobacco,
the nicotine,
and reactive
oxygen species,
and inactivation
of ant proteases.
And it's a little
bit more busy,
but it's also a
nice illustration of
what I just said.
So in emphysema, the
lungs have increased
compliance and decreased
in elasticity.
Their elastic walls
have been broken down.
So it results in
obstruction and
air trapping.
So when you exhale
the person with COP
with emphysema,
the terminal
bronchials collapse
because of a
radial traction,
if you will, and
the air is trapped
dis because
where the elastic
tissue was lost.
These people have very
big voluminous lungs
and often overlaps
the heart anteriorly.
In the smokers, the
upper two thirds of
lungs are more severely
affected. I think
I mentioned that.
When you look at a
lung with emphysema,
and I'm sure you've
seen some in
the cadaver lab
last year because
I know I did.
They're larger
villi and they
can be seen on
the cut surface.
And again, if it's
really severe,
they can become bloods or
big blister like spaces.
Microscopically, what
are you going to see?
Really abnormally
large alveoli,
which have very
thin septa and
a little bit of
center asofibrosis.
Sometimes when
they're big enough,
you'll see bul, and that
compresses the bronchials
and the vessels.
So this is the
cut surface.
One on the left is a
center acinar emphysema.
And you see it says E,
emphasema is damaged.
E is surrounded by
relatively spared
albular spaces.
And the one on
the right is
panacinar emphysema,
most likely due to
Alpha one antitrsin
deficiency,
and it's the entire
lobule that's affected.
This is the histology.
If you looked at a
normal lung on the left,
you see a lot of
little holes,
a lot of red and pink
and little holes.
And those are air spaces.
Those are violan stuff.
When you have an
emphaseminus lung
on the right, look
at what happens.
The holes become a lot
bigger because the
walls have broken down,
and all the elastic
has been chewed up,
and so you have,
irregular air spaces.
Clinically, these
patients tend
there's a
spectrum in COPD,
and they tend to be
called pink puffers.
They have a dysmia,
which is progressive and
they hyperventilate.
They're known to have
barrel shaped chests.
So because they have that,
it's hard to hear
breath sounds.
It's distant. They could
have right heart
failure eventually.
And classically, they're
going to be sitting in
a forward
hunching position
with prolonged expiration,
and they breathe
through pursed lips,
which is where
the name pink
puffer comes from.
They don't have
much of a cough,
like you would in
chronic bronchitis,
which we'll talk about.
But they do have
some cough.
Overdistenion
of the lungs is
severe and their diffusion
capacity is low.
Because these
people are spending
so much energy
trying to breathe,
there is weight
loss involved,
and many of these people
look very, very thin.
Again, I mentioned the
subplural blebs and
that can lead to a
fatal pneumothorax,
depending on
how big it is.
And I'm not talking now
about the pneumothorax
as young men,
which was the distal
the paraseptal emphysema.
So here again are
the pulmonary function
test readings.
And it's important to know
the ABGs to be
familiar with them.
Notice that it could
be normal the pH,
or if there's
decrease in CO two,
you can basically there's
a respiratory
alkalosis that
occurs for the most part.
And here's a nice side by
side x ray pictures
where you see what's
known as hyperlcency.
It's a lot darker.
There's more air. Air is
black, so it's darker.
And the AP or
the anterior posterior
diameter is increased.
The heart, if you see in
the emphase it looks
like it's vertically
oriented.
It looks thinner,
looks like it's thin,
but that's just an
illusion because
of how big the lungs are.
And the diaphragm is
kind of flattened.
So those are big features
in the x ray of emphasem.
Let's move on to
chronic bronchitis,
which is another
smoker problem,
and it's really
defined clinically.
You don't really go make
biopsies on these people,
but it's a persistent
cough with
sputin production for
at least three months
in at least two
consecutive years,
and there's no
identifiable cause.
Of course, when
it's long standing,
we have problems
with hypoxemia,
even pulmonary
hypertension,
and again, corpomonali.
Here's a nice cartoon of
the pathogenesis of
chronic bronchitis.
Basically what
initiates is
exposure to some stimulus,
noxious stimulus,
mainly tobacco smoke,
but other things
can cause it.
And you develop a
hypersecretion of mucus,
and why do you develop
a hypersecretion of mucus?
Because there
is hypertrophy
of the submucosal glands.
Hypertrophy, if
you remember,
from last year
is an increase
in the size of the glands.
This could involve
inflammatory mediators,
and it's stimulated by
proteases and
metallic proteases.
There's also
an increase in
goblet cells in
the small airways,
and so that will lead to
excess mucus
production and
airway obstruction.
In addition to
the pathogenesis,
many people have
been found to have
an acquired
cystic fibrosis
translan conductance
regulator dysfunction.
It seems that smoking can
lead to this dysfunction,
and so you end
up secreting
abnormal dehydrated
mucus that
really makes the
severity a lot worse.
Again, inflammation
is a problem.
If you inhale
something that
can you have
chronic bronchitis,
it can cause
damage to cells.
Acute and chronic
inflammation can occur,
including the
neutrophils, which
obviously are acute and
lymphocytes and macapages.
Once again, infection
does not initiate it,
but infections
can certainly
exacerbate the
chronic bronchitis.
And very simply
tomato smoke
damages the
airway lining and
you get chronic
inflammation and
it also interferes
with the cilia.
Remember that the
upper airway anyway,
has pseudostratified
ciliated epithelium,
and it really kind of
destroys the cilia.
And so therefore, you
cannot clear your
mucus and you're at
increased risk of
infection because that's
the whole point
of the cilia
to help you move
things out.
What do you see grossly?
Well, Usually in
chronic bronchitis,
you would see
very red lungs,
hyperemic, they're
swollen and dmucus
membranes are demets.
There's there's
excessive mucinous or even
mucopurulent secretions.
They may have secretions
with pus filling,
the bronchi and
bronchiols.
Now, this is the
microscopic image,
and there's a lot of
information here,
and I just want to talk
about a few things.
Of course, I
just mentioned
the chronic inflammation.
What happens is that
you get a thickening of
the bronchiol wall
because they're
smooth muscle,
hypertrophy, enlargement,
and there's fibrosis.
As I mentioned,
there's increasing
goblet cells.
Goblet cell hyperplasia.
And this enlargement
of mucus clans, also,
all of this makes
the red index an
important measure. Now,
they don't do this.
They don't take
a biopsy and
do a red index
on a person with
chronic barchitis,
but this is the
traditional way
of explaining it.
The red index is
the thickness
of the mucus glands.
Over the thickness of
the bronchial wall
between the epithelium
and cartilage.
And then the picture
on the right, you
see that it's B C,
here's B, and here C.
These are the
glands right there,
and it's the ratio between
that and the wall,
basically, the epithelium
and cartilage.
And you can tell
bigger the mucous
glands are,
the more they take up,
the ratio will
be different.
Normally, it's 0.4, and
it will be increased
in chronic bronchitis.
You're also going to have
narrowing of the
bronchiols with
mucus plugs and
inflammation and fibrosis.
It can be very severe
so that the lumens are
totally obliterated
because of fibrosis
or scarring,
and that's called
broncultis obliterates.
Also remember smoke
does cause squamous
metaplasia,
metaplasia being
a change from
one adult cell
type to another,
which can then lead to
dysplasia because
of the smoking.
Clinically, you
have what's known
at the other end of
the spectrum, a
blue bloater.
This person usually has a
persistent cough
with sputum,
a lot of sputum,
hypercapnia hypoxemia
and cyanosis.
The retained carbon
dioxide makes their skin
blue and they
have chronic
respiratory acidosis.
That's a little
different and
decrease 02 sats
from hypoxemia.
They tend to be
a little bit on
the stocky base side.
Again, the same thing
as in emphysema,
you're going to
have an increase in
total lung capacity in
residual volume
and a decrease
in FEV one over FVC ratio.
These people tend to get
infections more and they
can develop pulmonary
hypertension corpuminali.
Death can occur either
from heart failure
or even from acute
respiratory failure.
This chart again
is from Robins,
and it's a nice
way to compare
bronchitis and emphysema,
both are considered
COPD side to side.
How do you treat them?
Well, I'm a pathologist,
so I don't usually
treat people,
but you want to, if
you are treating them,
tell them to
stop smoking if,
which is easier
said than done.
Oxygen therapies use
bronchodilators,
lung acting ones,
which I'm sure you'll
learn in pharmacology,
with inhaled
scortico steroids,
antibiotics for infection,
physical therapy
and alectomy.
And some patients may
even need lung
transplantation.
The next one is asthma.
This is the third one,
and it's our chronic,
recurrent inflammatory
disease of the airway,
so you get recurrent,
wheezing, breathlessness,
tightness in the
chest, and cough.
Affects the bronchi and
terminal bronchioles
and usually more so in
children than adults.
It can be seasonal,
it can be induced by
exercise or by
certain drugs,
occupational, or it
can be in smokers.
Basically, the whole
thing is that you have
an increased airway
responsiveness to
many different
stimuli that
leads to
bronchoconstrictions
that's episodic.
It doesn't constrict
all the time.
It's episodes, and
airflow obstruction,
there's inflammation
again of
the walls and increase
in mucus secretion.
No matter what
asthma you have,
what type of weather
and we're going
to talk about
different types.
The episodes of
the bronchospasms
have diverse triggers.
They could be
respiratory infections,
and irritants, and
cold air stress
or exercise.
So the first type
of asthma is called
a topic or
extrinsic asthma,
and it's based on
allergen sensitization
and immune activation.
Many of these
patients often have
allergic rhinitis or ema
or some family history.
And it's triggered by
environmental
allergens like dusts
and pollens, et cetera.
And along with
other pro inflammatory
environmental things
such as if they get
a respiratory
viral infection
on top of it, that
makes it worse.
And this type of assumin
usually occurs
in childhood.
This is a TH two
mediated IGE response
hypersensitivity,
which is a type one.
So if you did a skin test
with the dust
or the pollens,
it will get a wheal
and flare reaction
really get real big
area of redness.
It can also be diagnosed.
These people have a high
total serum IGE level.
And or evidence of
allergen sensitization
by using the radio
ergosber test,
the rasts, because
they detect the
presence of
IG antibodies for
whatever allergen
they're testing for.
The other kind
of asthma is
called non atopic and it's
intrinsic in which there's
no evidence of allergen
sensitization,
and usually the skin
tests are negative.
This type of asthma
can be triggered
by especially a virus,
respiratory tract
infections.
Some of them are named
in the parentheses.
It can be also inhaled
air pollutants
may contribute to the
inflammation sometimes,
and can also be
attacks that
are triggered by
cold and exercise.
Now, there's one I
want to talk about
that's drug induced,
and it's rare.
It's aspergin
sensitive asthma.
Also it occurs with SDs.
And you get basically
asthmatic attacks
and urticaria,
if you remember, hives
from the skin pathology.
This usually occurs
in patients who have
recurrent rhinitis
and nasal polyps.
That's another
thing they have.
It does so via,
as you know,
aspirin inhibits
the CC pathway
leading to PGE
two decrease,
and that inhibits enzymes
that generate pro
inflammatory mediators.
The other type of
asthma is occupational,
which is obviously
whatever your
occupation is.
I noticed that
formaldehyde is in red.
If you've had if
any of you had
allergies in the
anatomy lab,
you know, it may
have been triggered
by some formaldehyde
if it was if you
breathe of it.
So Usually repeated
exposures,
minute amounts will
cause it to happen.
And there's different
mechanisms of action,
like type one or
hypersensitive
response, et cetera.
So the pathogenesis.
Well, in atopic asthma,
which is the more
common form,
I already told you it's
a TH two mediated
IGE response to
an environmental gen. And
usually those people are
genetically predisposed.
So you get the inflammation
in the airway.
That causes the
airway dysfunction
because there's release
of inflammatory mediators,
and there is
what's known as
remodeling of
the airway wall.
When it's severe,
there's going
to be increased secretion
of growth factors,
which will make the
mucus glands get larger.
You're going
to have smooth
muscle proliferation
and angiogenesis of
new blood vessels
and fibrosis.
The fundamental
problem, again,
I want to repeat
is an exaggerated
TH two response to
some normally harmless
environmental anergis,
although cigarette smoke,
which could induce
it is not harmless.
These TH two cells will
secrete cytokines
and and that
promotes inflammation
and stimulates B cells
to make IGE and
other antibodies.
Cytokines stimulate
production of
IG as I just said,
and also IL
five and IL 13,
which all do
different things
as noted in the
parentheses.
And in the end,
the IGE binds to
the FC receptors on
subducosal mass cells,
and that causes
a release of
branos and production of
cytokines and
other mediators.
And altogether, that is
the immediate
hypersensit early phase,
and then follows
the late phase.
This is basically I've
divided in early phase
means that that part
of it is the broncho
constriction,
the increase in mucus,
some dasodlation,
and some increased
vascular permeability.
The broncho
constriction is
triggered by
direct stimulation
of gal or parasympathetic
receptors
underneath the epithelium
both centrally
and locally.
Late phase reaction means
that now after
that's happened,
we get recruitment of
white blood cells,
especially eosinophils,
neutrophils, and even
some more T cells.
Now, on the
right hand side,
I just wrote down
some mediators,
you may want to know
about the bronchospa
that are important
in bronchospasm,
they know they
are because it's
supported by drug
therapy success.
They have an they have
drugs against these
mediators that work.
So there's
leukotriin, C 4d4e4,
which is our mediators
that cause prolonged
bronchoconstriction,
increased vascular
permeability,
and increased
mucus secretion.
Acetocholn, that
causes airway smooth
muscle constriction,
directly because
it directly
stimulates muscular
receptors.
Interlocin five is very
important and important to
remember that
it's associated
with peripheral
blood eosinophilia.
And then there's
galactin ten,
which is released
from the eosinophils
and forms what are known
as charcoal
laden crystals,
which I'll show you more
pictures of,
which are very,
very strong reducers of
inflammation and mucus.
So this is taken
directly from Robins,
and it just
shows a picture
of the normal ARA is A,
B is airway and asthma.
C is kind of like the
early well, it's
triggering,
and then D down
there is the
immediate phase
with the minutes.
And I just put down
some other
mediators that have
less contributions
on the list here,
just for your so you
know what they are.
But this is
basically what's
happening in visual form.
People have
genetic susceptibilities
with asthma.
It's often something
that occurs,
and it's often
associated with
other allergic diseases
like rhinitis,
allergic rhinitis
and eczema.
And all these
four points down
here are examples of
genetic variants,
and you don't need
to memorize these.
I just want you to
know that there are
genetic polymorphisms,
and they have found
them on different
chromosomes,
and they've also
seen that there's
class two HLA alleles that
are linked to IGE
antibiic production, et.
I just wanted you to
have that and know that.
But again, these
are things that
are still being
investigated.
And of course, environmental
factors because
most asthma people live
in urban populations.
And the theory behind
that is the cities
have more pollution,
and they may be
allergens that
initiate the TH
two response.
And another theory
is that in the city,
young children
have limited
exposure to
certain antigens,
known as the
hygiene hypothesis.
So many children don't get
as much microbial exposure
during their early life.
And they feel that
microbial exposure during
early life can reduce
later allergic diseases.
Infections I
already mentioned
can cause acute
exacerbations,
and young children
who develop
viral respiratory tract
infections seem to
have a really big ten
to 30 fold increase
in developing asthma.
The aloogy After this
is going to
happen over time.
It's not going
tohapp immediately,
but if you have repeated
episodes of asthma,
you're going to
get structural
changes in the
bronchial wall.
This is known as
airway remodeling,
where you get
both hypertrophy
and hyperplasia,
which means
increase in size
and increase in
the number of
bronchial smooth
muscles with
an increased
extracellular matrix.
There's going to be
injury to the epithelium,
more vascularity,
sub epithelial
or subnucosal
ucscln enlargement,
and gaba cells are
also increased,
and you'll get
eventually fibrosis
because of deposition of
Type one and
three collagens.
So your wall is going
to get thicker.
And so this is like saying
the same thing, but
it's in Pictorial.
This is also from Robins,
a very close picture of
a bronchus from somebody
who has asthma.
It's showing
airway remodeling,
goblet cell hypoplasia
is the green arrow.
And here you see all
these big vaculs here.
There's too many. Should
be as much as that.
Sube basement
membrane fibrosis
is the black arrow,
and that's
this thick pink line
that's going on.
That should be a
very thin line.
It shouldn't
be this thick.
Easynophilic
inflammation is yellow.
These are all these
little red dots.
These are eosinophals
that are in the area,
and the muscle
hypertrophy,
is the blue, you see
the smooth muscle is a lot
more prominent
than it should be.
In the sputum or if you do
bronchial lavage or a
person with atopic asthma,
you can find these
things that I mentioned,
charcoal laden crystals,
and they're made of
esmphl drive
protein coltu ten.
The other thing
you can find
are something known
as Kirschen spirals,
and they think that can
result from extrusion of
mucus plugs from the sub
epithelial mucous gland
ducts of bronchials.
These are important
findings in
the sputum and the
bronchial lavage.
Clinically, if somebody
has an asthma attack,
it can last up to
several hours with
very tight chest
tightness and dysma.
The wheezing is usually
expiratory wheezing,
you hear it
upon expiration
and coughing with
or without sputum.
And sometimes patients
with asthma have
these symptoms at a low
level all the time.
Sometimes they just
have severe attacks.
The diagnosis is based on
demonstrating that
there's an increase
in error flow obstruction
and difficulty with
exhalation with
the wheezing and
the expiration and
in expiration.
In those who have
atopic asthma,
there isocyoplia in
the peripheral blood
and eosinophils,
and Kirschen
spirals and harpou,
crystals in the sputum.
There's something
that can happen
called pulsus paradoxus,
and it's when this solid
blood pressure drops
more than 10 millimeters
of mercury during
inspiration.
Because what happens
basically is parts of
the airways tighten swell
when they're
having an attack,
and lungs will try to
over inflate to respond.
This puts pressure
on veins that carry
the unoxyated blood from
the hearts to the lungs.
And so there's
backup of blood in
the right ventricle that
causes pressure on
the right side,
which presses against
the left side.
And then the increased
negative pressure in
the lungs puts extra
pressure on the
left ventricle.
There's also increased
AP diameter
during attacks,
and the worst
kind of asthma is
what's called
status asthmaticus,
which is very severe
bronchoconstriction
that does not
respond to drugs,
and it is the
most severe form.
It can last days to weeks,
and it certainly can be
fatal and is something
that is very dangerous
to the person.
In asthma, labs
will initially show
a respiratory
alkalosis that
can progress later to
respiratory asmosis,
if bronchospasm
is not relieved.
And sometimes,
unfortunately, they have to
be intubated and
mechanically ventilated.
I if the person is
not responding who
has normal PH or
respiratory acidosis
because they're
obviously they're
not normalizing.
There's eosinophilia,
positive skin tests for
algens for the atopic.
And the treatment depends
on how severe it is.
You can use
bronchodilators,
glu corticoids,
leukotriin antagonists.
Now there's new therapies
for very severe
which are target
the inflammatory
mediators like IL five.
Antibodies that
block that.
The last one is
bronchiectasis.
This is along, which
as you can tell,
I hope you can tell
it's abnormal.
It's got big holes in it.
It's very dilated
bronchials.
This is when you
have destruction of
smooth muscle and
elastic tissue
basically by
inflammation because
of persistent or
severe infections,
and you get this
permanent dilation
of the bronchial
and bronchials.
The association here is
with chronic
necrotizing infections.
And what happens
is They have
impaired clearing
secretion so that
they pull and additional
to the obstruction,
there's inflammation
leading to
necrosis, fibrosis,
and dilation.
It's not as common
now as it was
years ago because now
we have better
antibiotics.
But there are some
conditions where
it can be associated with.
One of them is
a couple of them are
a cystic fibrosis,
primary ciliary
dyskinesia,
and cartahano syndrome,
which I'll talk about.
And these are
hereditary or
congenital conditions.
Severe necrotizing
pneumonia of
any type caused
by anything,
bacteria virus or fungi
can end up in
bronchiactsis,
or bronchial
obstruction if
there's a tumor
or form body,
and usually
that cont cause
local bronchiactsis
to the area that's
blocked off.
Immune disorders like
rheumatoid arthritis,
and lupus,
et cetera, and even
post transplant
have been associated with
bronchiactsis, as well.
But up to half
the cases are
idiopathic and seem to be
a dysfunctional
host immunity to
infectious agents that go
on that lead to
chronic inflammation.
So just a little bit about
the three hereditory
conditions
I talked about,
cystic fibrosis.
I don't expect
you to know all
about it just
mentioning it.
It is an autosomal
recessive disorder and
cystic fibrosis is
the most common cause
of bronchiectasis in
the United States.
There's a defect in
the CFTR for chloride ion.
So there's ion
transport defect,
and you can see that in
the right hand picture.
So you end up with
dehydrated thick
secretions,
and that's going to affect
the mucocilary clearance,
and it's going to lead
to airway destruction.
These people will develop
chronic bacterial
infections,
so there's more damage.
The bronchi are
markedly dilated,
and sometimes the
bronchials become
obliterated because of
scarring or fibrosis,
again, that's the
bronchiolitis obliterans.
We're not going to do
a whole thing on
cystic fibrosis,
but just so you know
it's associated
with salty tasting skin.
They usually do
a chloride test,
a sweat test, and
meconium ilus which
is in the newborn.
Then there's primary
ciliar dyskinesia,
which some people say is
the same thing
as cartagena,
but it's a little
bit different.
In primary ciliar dc
kinesia, by the way,
all these are to recess,
so that's easy
to remember.
You have mutations in
the cilia in the
silly function.
Usually it's mutations in
the dinin arm
in the cilia.
And because the cilia are
poorly functioning or
not working at all,
that's going to
prevent mucociliary
clearance.
You're going to retain
your secretions
and have a current
infection.
Half of the people
with primary
ciliary dyskinesia
have Cartagena syndrome.
The thing is, the
Cartagena syndrome,
because cilia
are needed in
embryogenesis to
properly rotate
organs in the chest
and the abdomen,
they will be born
with stis versus or
basically a
dextrocardia heart
on the right
side and male in
fertilogy because of
sperm dysmotility.
Bronchictss due
to infections,
most common
worldwide is TB,
and there is
something called
allergic bronchopulmonary
astroglysis,
which is a hyper
immune reaction
to aspergillus,
the fungus,
that leads the
sensitization leads to
activation of TH
two helper T cells,
and you get cytokines
and you get
eosinophils and
another white cells.
These people will have
high serum IGE levels.
Also, as an asthma,
a very eosinophilic airway
inflammation and
mucus plugs.
Sometimes you can
see the fungus
on special stains inside
the mucus of the
dilated bronchi
when you get
the aspiration
or the bronchial levage.
Bronchial obstruction,
as I mentioned,
tumor or foreign bodies,
or a big mucus paction,
can cause local
bronchiatsis,
and I mentioned the
immune disorders before.
Morphologically, what
are we going to see?
It's mostly in the
lower lobes and most
severe in the more distal
bronchii and bronchials.
The airways are
dilated, big time.
Usually if you follow
a bronchus with when
you're dissecting,
you can only follow up to
about 22 to 3 centimeters
up under the
pleural surface,
but these dilated airways
are all the way dilated
to the pleural surface.
And so you're going to
see dilated bronchi that
look like they're
cysts and they're
filled with mucopurulent
secretions.
And as you would
expect histologically,
you're going to see
acute and chronic
inflammation
in the walls of
the bronchi and
the bronchiols.
There will be declamation
of the epithelial.
There's going to be
loss of epithelium.
But the remaining
epithelium,
there will be
squamous metaplasia
because of
inflammation and
the lack and that will
also worsen the
negocllary clearance.
There's going to be
necrotizing ulceration.
You can lead to
abscess formation
and chronic cases
can show fibrosis.
That can again lead to
total obliteration
of lumens.
Many patients have mixed
for bacteria that are
cultured from bronchi,
but H influenza is
found in half of them,
and pseudomonas
ginosa is present in
12 to 30% of
sputum cultures of
people who have
bronchiectasis.
And these are
pretty dramatic
pictures that I found,
and you can see that
pus green look to it.
And these people will
really cough up a,
a lot of sputum.
And look how big and
dilated those bronchi are.
Clinically, the person has
severe persistent
cough with
very abundant
foul smelling
and sometimes
bloody sputum.
And they tend to
have paroxysms
of cough, especially
in the morning.
Reason being there's
a drainage of
all the secretions in
the pus from laying down,
and then when
they get up, it
just brings up the cough.
So these people have,
as you would imagine,
dynia Northopna,
if it's severe,
they could have
hemoptysis,
and they will
make it cyanotic.
But because we have
better antibiotics
and we do
physical therapy,
which is like the pumping
on the chest or
banging on the chest
kind of thing,
the prognosis is improved.
So the historical core
pulmonale that used
to happen of brain absses
are not as frequent
as they used to be.
This is a chart
comparing all
four, the anatomic site,
their pathological
changes,
the etiology and
the sign symptoms,
please take a look at
this and study it.
I think it's a
good side by side.
Now for some questions,
We're starting with
a 12-year-old girl.
I'm going to ask
you to pause
the recording so you
can read the
whole question.
I'm just going to go
through it continuously.
So when you get
to the question,
just pause so
you can read it.
This girl has a history
of coughing and wheezing.
She's got repeated attacks
of difficulty breathing,
especially in the spring.
So we're leaning
very strongly to
a certain diagnosis
here. She's a febril.
She has hyper
resonant lungs,
and the chest x ray shows
lucency of all
the lung fields.
She's an elevated serum,
IGE level and esidophlia.
Okay. Putting this
all together,
the question
then asks what
phytological feature
is most likely
to characterize this
patient's acute condition.
So I think by now,
you probably figure out
that this is asthma,
and it's probably
atopic asthma
because there's
a acidophilu.
So the answer
should come to
mind that it is
D as in David,
thickening of bronchial
epithelial
basement membrane
and hypertrophy of
the bronchial
smooth muscle.
A, which is dilation
of respiratory bronchial,
a distension of alveoli
refers to emphysema.
B, dilation of
bronchi with
inflammatory
destruction of walls
would refer to
bronchiectasis.
The C is about diffuse
alvular damage,
which is another session,
and E is most likely
going to do with some
type of pneumonia.
Okay. Next question.
For the past six years,
45-year-old non
smoking woman,
we're told that she has
the PI Z Z phenotype.
So the answer is
like kind of
given to you that
she's Alpha one
antitrypsin deficiency.
So the question is,
what is most
likely present?
So the association you
should put in
your mind for
anti Alpha one
antitypsin deficiency
is E as in Edward,
panacinar emphysema.
D, center acinar emphysema
would be related
to smoking.
And this is not
cystic fibrosis.
Don't get it
confused with that,
that would be more like
bronchiactss. Okay.
Here's a
35-year-old woman.
She's had a lot
of necrotizing,
severe pneumonia since
she was a child,
and all these organisms,
hemophols, syphococs,
pedomons, ratio.
Now she has had a
cough for weeks at
a time and she produces
a lot of pergulo sputum.
Then there's a
bronchogram that shows
marked dilation of
the right lower
low bronchit.
So this is or should you
should recognize as a
case of bronchiactsis.
The question
then asks you,
what is the most
likely cause
of the dilation
in the patient?
So because this is
a bronchiactsis,
the correct answer
would be D,
as in David,
destruction of
bronchial walls by
recurrent inflammation.
A unopposed action of
neutrophil derived
elastase would
have to be in emphysema.
And we've never
talked about
any congenital weakening
of supporting structures.
It's not diffuse
alvular damage.
And there's no talk of
ein This is not asthma.
So we're not talking
about eosinophil.
So the answer is D.
Next is a 20-year-old,
and he's jogging
and he falls
down and he becomes
markedly short of breath.
They bring him to the ER.
There are no breath
sounds over the
right chest.
The chest x ray shows
the shift of the mete stim
from right to left.
They insert the right
chest tube and
air rushes out.
So this is a spontaneous
pneumothorax in
a young man.
He's 20-years-old.
So what obstructive lung
disease do we
associate with that?
Going back to the
different types,
the one that is
associated with it
is paraseptal or the
other name for it,
distal Astin emphysema,
which is E as an N word.
Centra Astin
mhsema, again,
will be more likely
to do with smoking.
So the answer is E. And
a 50-year-old man has had
increasing dyspnea and
weight loss. Okay.
So he's probably what
they would call
a pink puffer.
He's a smoker, two pack
of cigarettes,
stake for 20 years,
and he has a
barrel chest and
his FEV one FEC
ratio has decreased.
So he's got an
obstructive process,
barrel chest, he
has emphysema.
So which of the
following is
most likely to contribute
to the pathogenesis?
And you look at pause
and look at the answers.
And the one that should
come to you is B as
in boy release of
elastase from
neutrophils, okay?
Impaired hepatic
release of
Alpha one antitrypsin is
antitrpsin one deficiency,
which would be
panacin emphysema.
Abnormal epithelial cell
chloride ion transport,
which we see, is
a cystofibrosis,
which would be
bronchiectasis,
and decreased
ciliary motility
with irregular dynamos
also bronchiectasis
and macrophage recruitment
and interferon
gamma release,
that would have to
do with granulominus
disease.
So the answer
is B as in boy.
So this is the
summary side slide.
Again, there's these
four major ones
with some subdivisions,
and the lecture
feedback form,